<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="https://burakayy.com/blog/tag/arduino/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="https://burakayy.com/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2026-01-21T17:58:02+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://burakayy.com/blog/tag/arduino/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">Burak Ayyorgun | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>My Blog for Technical Projects</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How to get started with Engineering</title>
      <link href="https://burakayy.com/blog/How-to-start-Arduino" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to get started with Engineering" />
      <published>2024-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://burakayy.com/blog/How-to-start-Arduino</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://burakayy.com/blog/How-to-start-Arduino">&lt;p&gt;Hi, my name is Burak Ayyorgun and I wanted to share how I started with Engineering and give advice how you guys might want to start. The main goal is to find what you are interested in &amp;amp; how to chase your own projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;who-am-i-and-how-i-got-started&quot;&gt;Who am I, and how I got Started&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I wanted to give a quick introduction and how I started engineering. Currently, I’m a high school student and I first started my engineering projects in 7th grade for as cheaply as possible. I had acquired an interest in electricity and how electronics components work. So, I started to teach myself these concepts using free resources on the internet; I would dismantle toy trains, cars, or even radios for there electronic parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Driven to learn how they worked, I kept a journal to document my progress. I taught myself the physics behind why motors work, or why electrons flow and why batteries work. It all seemed very attractive to me. Once I learned the fundamentals, I got myself electronics kits, which contained components like transistors, capacitors, resistors, LEDs, and many more. After I went through a few tutorials on YouTube, I experimented my making my own circuits. I tried to make transistor calculators, timer circuits, and so much more exciting things. Around this time, I got myself an Arduino kit (from my holiday money) and I slowly started to learn embedded programming. At first, I thought it was kind of cheating in engineering, because you could accomplish a hard task in electronics like blinking an LED, with a couple lines of code I felt that I wasn’t being compelled to learn HOW things worked. However, once I eventually moved onto more complicated projects (mostly robotics related ones) I realized the power of Arduino. Having a single board, capable of accomplishing almost anything just via code, is an incredibly valuable tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I am explaining this is to show that you &lt;strong&gt;don’t need an expensive budget to start engineering, nor do you need to take an engineering class.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;ins&gt;All you need is a passionate interest in learning, be motivated to try new challenging topics, patiently dedicated, and a good source that is tailored for self-learners, hence this course!&lt;/ins&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;getting-started-with-arduino&quot;&gt;Getting Started with Arduino&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you have an interest in engineering and programming and you want to start an Arduino project. The first thing you will need is some knowledge of electronics and some electronic parts to experiment with. I started by making or harvesting my own parts, but I suggest you start with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/EL-CK-002-Electronic-Breadboard-Capacitor-Potentiometer/dp/B01ERP6WL4/ref=asc_df_B01ERP6WL4/?tag=hyprod-20&amp;amp;linkCode=df0&amp;amp;hvadid=692875362841&amp;amp;hvpos=&amp;amp;hvnetw=g&amp;amp;hvrand=6781416287060863964&amp;amp;hvpone=&amp;amp;hvptwo=&amp;amp;hvqmt=&amp;amp;hvdev=c&amp;amp;hvdvcmdl=&amp;amp;hvlocint=&amp;amp;hvlocphy=9008161&amp;amp;hvtargid=pla-2281435178378&amp;amp;mcid=9cae1398299332c592e9e59d7108c20c&amp;amp;hvocijid=6781416287060863964-B01ERP6WL4-&amp;amp;hvexpln=73&amp;amp;th=1&quot;&gt;this Elegoo Electronics kit&lt;/a&gt;, which was my first kit as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you are looking for an electronics kit and an Arduino kit, I suggest you buy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/EL-KIT-008-Project-Complete-Ultimate-TUTORIAL/dp/B01EWNUUUA/ref=sr_1_2_sspa?crid=VT5GROVB1LF2&amp;amp;dib=eyJ2IjoiMSJ9.-TMWe7jTY1L2k9FBx9xn45aUF9NcSgBFiPQ6oaDLYt2Cznux_TU45wzwVYLmtrQWvKhuwpNk2ieKX1geRZraMWtNVoqnTx4C4q_RqhIwnmbe8hn17AkgF8zYNcgfb_CvpT6UWFi6eoN_0UrRKqI-sRw69S_kW7wrtEl9hPT3SFsvGrgVgYOLl10HbuDTFnV1BOyb7fNHonPrdXVzEZVhe9oFCqCqbdoOSe4Pr3Cy6HrStJG_V0yfsNWnkwMOtRESIHrv8cvITSCVYqvUIvqWluq_inEOqArknVoMXDReyh4.WzOU8KAlagC6ySOcYMVzU1we36t-fgsKHFg-uUsQ2wo&amp;amp;dib_tag=se&amp;amp;keywords=elegoo+arduino+kit&amp;amp;qid=1726579233&amp;amp;s=electronics&amp;amp;sprefix=elegoo+arudino+kit%2Celectronics%2C60&amp;amp;sr=1-2-spons&amp;amp;sp_csd=d2lkZ2V0TmFtZT1zcF9hdGY&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;this Ardunio kit&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;arduino-ide-installation&quot;&gt;Arduino IDE Installation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start programming we will need a &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;ntegrated &lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt;evelopment &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;nvironment (IDE), specifically, we will be using the official Arduino IDE. Currently, there are three ways you can program an Arduino, either use the original Arduino 1.X IDE, the new Arduino 2.X IDE, or use the Cloud based IDE. While you can go either route, I suggest you start with the original IDE, if you are a beginner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So first, please go to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arduino.cc/en/software#legacy-ide-18x&quot;&gt;Arduino Software Website&lt;/a&gt; and download the .exe file for your environment. The instructions that follow should be pretty straight forward. Just make sure to install the software on the PATH (if prompted), and you should be ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/arduinoEng/arduino_ide.png&quot; alt=&quot;ide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- - listing instructions
-
- --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-the-different-kinds-of-arduinos&quot;&gt;What are the Different Kinds of Arduinos?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you search up “Arduino” you will see a bunch of different images pop-up. In fact, at the time of writing, there are over 25 different types of Arduinos! Which means we have a lot to play around with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;layout-and-hardware-on-an-arduino&quot;&gt;Layout and Hardware on an Arduino&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction-to-electronics&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-electronics&quot;&gt;Introduction to Electronics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strong knowledge of Arduino prototyping requires a pretty good understanding of breadboard prototyping. I learned this with trial and error, but you can use plenty of free online resources. Furthermore, you will need an understanding of basic electronic components, like transistors, capacitors, resistors, LEDs, and general ciruit grounding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to learn this, the first lesson in this course is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-electronics&quot;&gt;Introduction to Electronics&lt;/a&gt;, please check it out if you are a beginner to Arduino and/or need a refresher with the link below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;arduino-programming-basics--arduino-code&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-programming&quot;&gt;Arduino Programming Basics | Arduino Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we can start with projects, we also need a quick summary of basic programming concepts, so you don’t get lost later on. If you’re already familiar with programming languages, then I suggest to skip this section. This section is only for simple and basic programming concepts; I plan on teaching more advanced porgamming via examples and projects because I believe in teaching with hands-on work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So please view &lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-programming&quot;&gt;this lesson&lt;/a&gt; for a simple introduction to programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hello-world-example&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-hello-world&quot;&gt;Hello World Example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To not discourage you, I wanted to provide a quick &lt;em&gt;“hello world”&lt;/em&gt; example of an Arduino Project, it will include some concepts we have covered in the previous lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-hello-world&quot;&gt;This link is the lesson for the Hello World Example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sensors-and-actuators&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-sensors&quot;&gt;Sensors and Actuators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To build your “toolbelt” for Arduino Projects, &lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-sensors&quot;&gt;this lesson is on “mini-tutorials”&lt;/a&gt; on how to operate/use different types of sensors with Arduino. I cover topics/sensors from simple photoresistors to sensors that require different libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am constantly updated this page, so it doesn’t cover all of the sensors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-sensors&quot;&gt;Arduino Sensors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ### Ardunio Code




### Future Projects --&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name></name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="arduino" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Hi, my name is Burak Ayyorgun and I wanted to share how I started with Engineering and give advice how you guys might want to start. The main goal is to find what you are interested in &amp;amp; how to chase your own projects.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How to get started with Engineering | Electronics</title>
      <link href="https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-electronics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to get started with Engineering | Electronics" />
      <published>2024-06-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-06-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-electronics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-electronics">&lt;p&gt;Welcome back; here I will introduce you to the fundamentals and basics of Electronics for Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To follow along, please refer to the introductory lesson to find the link to an Arduino Kit, which will contain plenty of electronic components and a breadboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-a-breadboard-work&quot;&gt;How Does a BreadBoard Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A breadboard’s purpose is to help with efficiency when prototyping a circuit; instead of having to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solder&quot;&gt;solder&lt;/a&gt; every component, without knowing the circuit will work, wouldn’t it be nice to have a “plug-n-play” set up where you can easily interchange components?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the breadboard comes to the rescue!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a diagram of how the various pins on your board are connected:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/arduinoEng/breadboardLayout.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, breadboards have two sets of horizontal strips that run across the long side, each usually labelled with a red or blue strip. These are generally used for 
power, providing current to your circuit; however, these are not directly connected to the pins on the inside. I will explain how this works further, with examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/arduinoEng/breadboard1.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, referring to both of the diagrams above, each pin along a column is connected. But pins across rows are not connected. Furthermore, pins that cross the barrier
in the middle are also not connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This setup provides a framework which you can easily and systematically design your own circuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-resistors-work&quot;&gt;How Do Resistors Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resistor are an electronic component that, as the name implies, restricts and resists the flow of electrons in a circuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how does this work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, each &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electrical_conductor&quot;&gt;conductive material&lt;/a&gt; has its own properties, which results in each material conducting electricity
slightly differently. Thus, each material will also resist electricity differently. For example, copper is a very conductive material, which means 
it has a low resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a diagram showing the guts of a resistor:
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/arduinoEng/resistor1.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, there is some internal conductive material that is a mixture of various material with different properties.
This will result in the final material to have a &lt;strong&gt;different resistance than the pins&lt;/strong&gt; (connecting leads).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coloring on the resistor also has a meaning. It is some sort of code for the resistance. However, these are often not
standardized or hard to read and remember, so I usually don’t pay attention to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-a-transistor-work&quot;&gt;How Does a Transistor Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you search this up, probably the first “definition” you will come across is “ a transistor is an electronic switch”.
However, I have never liked this definition, as I think not only is it basic but it’s lacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a schematic diagram of a transistor:
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/arduinoEng/transistor1.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, there are three main pins (or leads): the collector, the base, and the emittor. Now, I could go into what each pin is,
but to understand a transistor, we have to go down to the atomic level and understand what’s &lt;strong&gt;in&lt;/strong&gt; a transistor first, then
we can understand what the pins mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand this, I think it is best if we tackle what a Diode is and how it works first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-does-a-diode-work&quot;&gt;How Does a Diode Work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A diode is an electronic component that basically restricts the flow of electrons, but only in one direction. It only allows electricity to flow in one direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a diagram of what the inside of a diode might look like, at an atomic level:
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/arduinoEng/diode1.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, let me explain what you are looking at. Basically, there are two materials inside of a diode: a n-type material and a p-type material.
But what does this mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well first, these materials are made up of mostly silicon. Which is something called a Semi-conductor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-are-semiconductors&quot;&gt;What Are Semiconductors?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are probably similar to conductors and insulators. But what are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semiconductor&quot;&gt;semiconductors&lt;/a&gt;? Well, simply put, semiconductors are materials (specifically metals) that can have both conductive, and less conductive properties, depending on the environment. Factors that might influence this are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;my-technical-report-on-photoresistors&quot;&gt;My Technical Report on Photoresistors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below, I have &lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/chem-paper&quot;&gt;linked a paper&lt;/a&gt; I had written in my sophomore year of high school to explain what photoresistors are and how they work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;assets/images/pdfs/ChemPaper2.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though I talk about photoresistors in that paper, I still explain semi-conductive materials and how various other materials, like phosphorus, are added to the silicon to achieve certain properties (mainly how there will be extra electrons in one mixture and a depletion, or holes, in another mixture).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refering back to this image of how the electrons will behave in a diode:
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/arduinoEng/diode1.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that due to the material properties of the p-type, it will create various holes (a lack of electrons in an atoms outer electron shell) and due to the properties of the n-type, there will be an excess of electrons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the key is notice what will happen (at an atomic scale) at the border/barrier between these two materials. Some of the free electrons nearest to the border will actually &lt;strong&gt;cross&lt;/strong&gt; over to the p-type material. So, after this interaction, the p-type material right-most side will be slightly negatively charged, and the left-most side of the n-type material will be positively charged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you might think that this process will continue, but it actually will not. See this transfer of initial electrons will create a charge barrier. This barrier will stop the electrons from the n-type to cross further to the p-type. But why does this happen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See, after the initial cross, like I said the right-most p-type side will be slightly negatively charged. So, when other electrons try to cross over to the p-type again, the negative charge created from the initial cross will repel further crosses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So currently, with no further charges applied, this diode will be locked in this charge state and no further electrons will flow (at least across the border; there might be small flow from electrons within the n-type).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s see what happens when we apply a charge, like from a battery, to the terminals of this diode (the positive side, p-type, is anode; negative side, n-type, is cathode).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/arduinoEng/diode1.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this first scenario, let’s say that the negative side of the battery was attached to the p-type side of the diode. So, electrons from the battery’s negative side will flow into the p-type side, filling in those holes, until electrons will reach the tiny negative barrier created from the initial electron exchange. This barrier acts like a wall, and inhibits electrons from flowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, let’s try to attach the battery in the opposite direction, where the negative side is on the cathode of the diode. The electrons flowing from the battery will push electrons from the n-type material, over the barrier and electricity can flow. But this can only happen past some voltage threshold, which depends on the diode characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-does-a-transistor-work-revisited&quot;&gt;How Does a Transistor Work, revisited&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, since we now know how diodes work, let’s see how we can apply this to understand how transistors work. Basically, transistors are two diodes in parallel. Now, don’t just think you can put two diodes in series on a breadboard and think you have created a transistor (this is actually something I believed in middle school). Below I will explain how a NPN Transistor works, but the same principles can be applied to PNP Transistors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the three pins on a transistor stand for the &lt;em&gt;base&lt;/em&gt; (the p-type material), &lt;em&gt;emitter&lt;/em&gt; (the n-type material), and the &lt;em&gt;collector&lt;/em&gt; (n-type material).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a diagram showing the electron arrangement of inside a transistor:
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/arduinoEng/arduino_transistor.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, it is really just two diodes ‘smushed’ together. As you can see, the p-type - n-type arrangements both create their own barriers. With a depletion zone in the middle (just a depletion of electrons, or holes). The physics of this should be the same as the barrier formed in a diode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s observe what happens when I apply a charge from the collector and emitter sides (which are kind of like the inputs and outputs of the transistor, at least in the context of where the electrons want to flow from, from one n-type to another n-type).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electrons will flow into the collector, pass (or break) the first barrier, but then be blocked by the barrier created by the second inter-junction (can you see why this happens? hint: analyze the charges that interact).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s observe what will happen when I add a positive charge to the base: again, electrons will pass over the first barrier and now have somewhere to go, the positive base; they will flow out of the base and complete the circuit. But this positive charge will also weaken the second barrier to the point that electrons will now be able to flow from the collector to the emitter, thus completing the circuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in this sense, a transistor is like a gate, it allows electrons to flow from one end to another only when a “key” (a positive charge on the base) is applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also PNP type transistors, which work very similarly, but instead of a positive charge on the base opening the gate, a negative charge will open the gate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, now that we have a basic understanding of semi-conductor materials, let’s learn about some other components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-a-led-work&quot;&gt;How Does a LED Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, this is stands for a &lt;strong&gt;L&lt;/strong&gt;ight &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;mitting &lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt;iode, and it does exactly as it sounds like: emits light by utilizing physical properties of certain materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quick-review-of-what-light-is&quot;&gt;Quick Review of what light is&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light is both a particle and a wave. But in this context light is just a photon being emitted from some energy source. Here, the photon is emitted when an electron drops in energy levels (from a higher orbital to a lower orbital).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, an LED is just a diode with some modifications. The key is the specific material(s) that the diode n-type and p-type is made of. And so when an electricity flows through this material, it will cause electrons to change energy levels (which will emit light). And depending on the particular materials, the emitted light will be a different frequency (which will change the ‘color’ of the light).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;creating-basic-circuits&quot;&gt;Creating Basic Circuits&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s circle back to using and applying what we learned about breadboards to create basic circuits. I will provide you with basic schematic reading skills and I will leave it up to you to build the circuit yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, below is a simple schematic that will show and apply basic components that we discussed earlier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets\images\arduinoEng\schematic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;sch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, it employs a transistor, resistors, diode, a button, and an LED (you can choose which ever color you’d like). Below is a list of corresponding symbols and their component:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notesreferences&quot;&gt;Notes/References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a few pages of notes from my old notebook related to How transistors work:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets\images\arduinoEng\notes3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets\images\arduinoEng\notes1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets\images\arduinoEng\notes2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets\images\arduinoEng\notes4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets\images\arduinoEng\notes5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name></name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="arduino" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Welcome back; here I will introduce you to the fundamentals and basics of Electronics for Engineering. To follow along, please refer to the introductory lesson to find the link to an Arduino Kit, which will contain plenty of electronic components and a breadboard. How Does a BreadBoard Work A breadboard’s purpose is to help with efficiency when prototyping a circuit; instead of having to solder every component, without knowing the circuit will work, wouldn’t it be nice to have a “plug-n-play” set up where you can easily interchange components? Well, the breadboard comes to the rescue! Below is a diagram of how the various pins on your board are connected: Usually, breadboards have two sets of horizontal strips that run across the long side, each usually labelled with a red or blue strip. These are generally used for power, providing current to your circuit; however, these are not directly connected to the pins on the inside. I will explain how this works further, with examples. So, referring to both of the diagrams above, each pin along a column is connected. But pins across rows are not connected. Furthermore, pins that cross the barrier in the middle are also not connected. This setup provides a framework which you can easily and systematically design your own circuits. How Do Resistors Work Resistor are an electronic component that, as the name implies, restricts and resists the flow of electrons in a circuit. But how does this work? Well, each conductive material has its own properties, which results in each material conducting electricity slightly differently. Thus, each material will also resist electricity differently. For example, copper is a very conductive material, which means it has a low resistance. Below is a diagram showing the guts of a resistor: As you can see, there is some internal conductive material that is a mixture of various material with different properties. This will result in the final material to have a different resistance than the pins (connecting leads). The coloring on the resistor also has a meaning. It is some sort of code for the resistance. However, these are often not standardized or hard to read and remember, so I usually don’t pay attention to them. How Does a Transistor Work If you search this up, probably the first “definition” you will come across is “ a transistor is an electronic switch”. However, I have never liked this definition, as I think not only is it basic but it’s lacking. Below is a schematic diagram of a transistor: As you can see, there are three main pins (or leads): the collector, the base, and the emittor. Now, I could go into what each pin is, but to understand a transistor, we have to go down to the atomic level and understand what’s in a transistor first, then we can understand what the pins mean. To understand this, I think it is best if we tackle what a Diode is and how it works first. How Does a Diode Work A diode is an electronic component that basically restricts the flow of electrons, but only in one direction. It only allows electricity to flow in one direction. Below is a diagram of what the inside of a diode might look like, at an atomic level: To start, let me explain what you are looking at. Basically, there are two materials inside of a diode: a n-type material and a p-type material. But what does this mean? Well first, these materials are made up of mostly silicon. Which is something called a Semi-conductor. What Are Semiconductors? You are probably similar to conductors and insulators. But what are semiconductors? Well, simply put, semiconductors are materials (specifically metals) that can have both conductive, and less conductive properties, depending on the environment. Factors that might influence this are My Technical Report on Photoresistors Below, I have linked a paper I had written in my sophomore year of high school to explain what photoresistors are and how they work. Even though I talk about photoresistors in that paper, I still explain semi-conductive materials and how various other materials, like phosphorus, are added to the silicon to achieve certain properties (mainly how there will be extra electrons in one mixture and a depletion, or holes, in another mixture). Refering back to this image of how the electrons will behave in a diode: We can see that due to the material properties of the p-type, it will create various holes (a lack of electrons in an atoms outer electron shell) and due to the properties of the n-type, there will be an excess of electrons. Now the key is notice what will happen (at an atomic scale) at the border/barrier between these two materials. Some of the free electrons nearest to the border will actually cross over to the p-type material. So, after this interaction, the p-type material right-most side will be slightly negatively charged, and the left-most side of the n-type material will be positively charged. Now, you might think that this process will continue, but it actually will not. See this transfer of initial electrons will create a charge barrier. This barrier will stop the electrons from the n-type to cross further to the p-type. But why does this happen? See, after the initial cross, like I said the right-most p-type side will be slightly negatively charged. So, when other electrons try to cross over to the p-type again, the negative charge created from the initial cross will repel further crosses. So currently, with no further charges applied, this diode will be locked in this charge state and no further electrons will flow (at least across the border; there might be small flow from electrons within the n-type). But let’s see what happens when we apply a charge, like from a battery, to the terminals of this diode (the positive side, p-type, is anode; negative side, n-type, is cathode). In this first scenario, let’s say that the negative side of the battery was attached to the p-type side of the diode. So, electrons from the battery’s negative side will flow into the p-type side, filling in those holes, until electrons will reach the tiny negative barrier created from the initial electron exchange. This barrier acts like a wall, and inhibits electrons from flowing. However, let’s try to attach the battery in the opposite direction, where the negative side is on the cathode of the diode. The electrons flowing from the battery will push electrons from the n-type material, over the barrier and electricity can flow. But this can only happen past some voltage threshold, which depends on the diode characteristics. How Does a Transistor Work, revisited So, since we now know how diodes work, let’s see how we can apply this to understand how transistors work. Basically, transistors are two diodes in parallel. Now, don’t just think you can put two diodes in series on a breadboard and think you have created a transistor (this is actually something I believed in middle school). Below I will explain how a NPN Transistor works, but the same principles can be applied to PNP Transistors. So, the three pins on a transistor stand for the base (the p-type material), emitter (the n-type material), and the collector (n-type material). Below is a diagram showing the electron arrangement of inside a transistor: As you can see, it is really just two diodes ‘smushed’ together. As you can see, the p-type - n-type arrangements both create their own barriers. With a depletion zone in the middle (just a depletion of electrons, or holes). The physics of this should be the same as the barrier formed in a diode. Let’s observe what happens when I apply a charge from the collector and emitter sides (which are kind of like the inputs and outputs of the transistor, at least in the context of where the electrons want to flow from, from one n-type to another n-type). The electrons will flow into the collector, pass (or break) the first barrier, but then be blocked by the barrier created by the second inter-junction (can you see why this happens? hint: analyze the charges that interact). Now, let’s observe what will happen when I add a positive charge to the base: again, electrons will pass over the first barrier and now have somewhere to go, the positive base; they will flow out of the base and complete the circuit. But this positive charge will also weaken the second barrier to the point that electrons will now be able to flow from the collector to the emitter, thus completing the circuit. So in this sense, a transistor is like a gate, it allows electrons to flow from one end to another only when a “key” (a positive charge on the base) is applied. There is also PNP type transistors, which work very similarly, but instead of a positive charge on the base opening the gate, a negative charge will open the gate. Ok, now that we have a basic understanding of semi-conductor materials, let’s learn about some other components. How Does a LED Work Simply put, this is stands for a Light Emitting Diode, and it does exactly as it sounds like: emits light by utilizing physical properties of certain materials. Quick Review of what light is Light is both a particle and a wave. But in this context light is just a photon being emitted from some energy source. Here, the photon is emitted when an electron drops in energy levels (from a higher orbital to a lower orbital). So, an LED is just a diode with some modifications. The key is the specific material(s) that the diode n-type and p-type is made of. And so when an electricity flows through this material, it will cause electrons to change energy levels (which will emit light). And depending on the particular materials, the emitted light will be a different frequency (which will change the ‘color’ of the light). Creating Basic Circuits Now let’s circle back to using and applying what we learned about breadboards to create basic circuits. I will provide you with basic schematic reading skills and I will leave it up to you to build the circuit yourself. Ok, below is a simple schematic that will show and apply basic components that we discussed earlier: As you can see, it employs a transistor, resistors, diode, a button, and an LED (you can choose which ever color you’d like). Below is a list of corresponding symbols and their component: Notes/References a few pages of notes from my old notebook related to How transistors work:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How to get started with Engineering | Arduino Programming</title>
      <link href="https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-programming" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to get started with Engineering | Arduino Programming" />
      <published>2024-06-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-06-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-programming</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-programming">&lt;p&gt;Now, if we want to be a good engineer in this day and age, we need to also know Computer Science. Arduino especially relies on this as this is how we will program the Board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so you probably have learned that Arduino is a development platform where you program a microcontroller. In the Arduino Environment, you do this with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.arduino.cc/learn/programming/reference/&quot;&gt;Arduino API&lt;/a&gt; (I am assuming you have downloaded the Arduino IDE in the previous lessons).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s dive in!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;arduino-sketches&quot;&gt;Arduino Sketches&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-look-at-the-arduino-ide&quot;&gt;A look at the Arduino IDE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you open the IDE, a new sketch should automatically appear. I will revist the details later, but you should see something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;loop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will go into how these work more later, but for now, just know that &lt;em&gt;void setup()&lt;/em&gt; is a place which you can put in code that you want to &lt;strong&gt;only run once at the beginning of the program&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;em&gt;void loop()&lt;/em&gt; is code for &lt;strong&gt;running continuously, in a loop&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most of the examples below, I will run them in setup(). &lt;strong&gt;And please note that in C++, you &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; end every line of code with a semicolon: “;”!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;variables&quot;&gt;Variables&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s say you had a bunch of data or information you wanted to store in a computer program, how would you do that? The simple way is to declare a &lt;em&gt;variable&lt;/em&gt; and the compiler (converting code to machine language) will the Arduino how to store a piece of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s simply what a variable is, a way to store information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see a few examples of the different types of info you can store:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Characters: store single characters, like ‘A’ or ‘$’&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Integers: stores integer numbers, like 20 or 4&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Floats: stores numbers with a decimal value, up to a certain degree, like 30.799 or 3.1415&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Doubles: can store even more deicmal values that floats, like 40.2991988476&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strings: is actually a class/object that stores a group of characters, like “Hello”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s see how we can use these in Arduino code (which is just C++) to store data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;age&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Bob&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;begin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;9600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;age&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;loop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, to declare an Integer, I use the keyword &lt;em&gt;int&lt;/em&gt; which signals that the variable name I enter after this will be an Integer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the below code will just declare a variable as an Integer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but to give the variable “height” a value, I must assign it using an equal sign and then put a corresponding value that matches the variable type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shoe_size&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after the variable type, I can name it any name I want, but it cannot contain ANY spaces, because any space seperates different parts of the program instructions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So all of the following are valid variable names:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;hello_world&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;silly_cat_videos&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;broken_latptop_that_I_dontWant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;camelBackNotationAlsoWorks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Woohoo_Big_summer_Blowout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floats, are not much different:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;float&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;this_is_a_float&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;10.9&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;float&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pi&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;3.1415&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And similarly, we can declare Strings and characters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Bob&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;initial&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;sc&quot;&gt;'B'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, with this tool of storing values in different types of variables, we can allow certain “programmable” ideas in our code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;arithmetic&quot;&gt;Arithmetic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to quickly touch on how we can use these variables in our program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding Integers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I just declared a new Integer Variable that is set to (equal sign) the sum (by using the + sign) of num1 and num2; This is how variables are used, you can just call their value later by refrencing their variable name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is how we can “increment” values:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How this works is that we set the memory space for num3 to what num3 is now plus num2. So every time this line of code is run, num2 is added to num3. The above is equavalent to the below, just a different notation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can also subtract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;multiply:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or divide:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;functions&quot;&gt;Functions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s say you have a piece of code that you want to use in multiple places in your program. There are two options: either copy/paste that code every time, or have some variable declaration that is actually a ‘mini program’ that will run that piece of code every time you call it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In modern programming, this is called &lt;em&gt;functions.&lt;/em&gt; In our Aruino C++ Programming language, here is how we make a function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;function1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now, every time I want to increment &lt;em&gt;number&lt;/em&gt;, instead of writing that line of code, and just simply call the function. Let’s break the above code apart; the &lt;em&gt;void&lt;/em&gt; key word refers to what this function will return. Every function can return a value, say I’m making a calculation, I can have a function return or output the final value of the math calculation. So when we define a function, we have to define which type of variable will it return. In this case, we made it a void (which is nothing, basically), which means this function will not return anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now let’s say I want to increment the number by a variable amount, how would I do that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;amount&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;function2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;addAmount&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;number&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;addAmount&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the parenthesis of the function, I can make a variable, in this case an Integer named &lt;em&gt;addAmount&lt;/em&gt;, and I can refrence that in the code. Here is how I would use this function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;function2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here, number is incremented by 4 instead of 1 in function1. All of the code is written in between the parenthesis, that is what defines the function code, everything in between the parenthesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Again, like all the other things, I will go in more detail once we actually start coding!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;arduino-sketches-revisited&quot;&gt;Arduino Sketches, revisited&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now that we know about functions, we can see that the &lt;em&gt;setup()&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;loop()&lt;/em&gt; sections in the Arduino IDE, are really just functions that are already defined for us. In these functions, we will write our main code, but we can also make our own functions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following lessons, we will write code to accomplish tasks using these two; this lesson was just an introductary lesson for coding.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name></name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="arduino" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Now, if we want to be a good engineer in this day and age, we need to also know Computer Science. Arduino especially relies on this as this is how we will program the Board. Ok, so you probably have learned that Arduino is a development platform where you program a microcontroller. In the Arduino Environment, you do this with the Arduino API (I am assuming you have downloaded the Arduino IDE in the previous lessons). Let’s dive in!! Arduino Sketches A look at the Arduino IDE So, if you open the IDE, a new sketch should automatically appear. I will revist the details later, but you should see something like this: void setup() { } void loop() { } I will go into how these work more later, but for now, just know that void setup() is a place which you can put in code that you want to only run once at the beginning of the program and void loop() is code for running continuously, in a loop. For most of the examples below, I will run them in setup(). And please note that in C++, you must end every line of code with a semicolon: “;”! Variables So, let’s say you had a bunch of data or information you wanted to store in a computer program, how would you do that? The simple way is to declare a variable and the compiler (converting code to machine language) will the Arduino how to store a piece of information. That’s simply what a variable is, a way to store information. Let’s see a few examples of the different types of info you can store: Characters: store single characters, like ‘A’ or ‘$’ Integers: stores integer numbers, like 20 or 4 Floats: stores numbers with a decimal value, up to a certain degree, like 30.799 or 3.1415 Doubles: can store even more deicmal values that floats, like 40.2991988476 Strings: is actually a class/object that stores a group of characters, like “Hello” Now, let’s see how we can use these in Arduino code (which is just C++) to store data. int age = 30; String name = &quot;Bob&quot;; void setup() { Serial.begin(9600); Serial.println(name); Serial.println(age); } void loop() { } As you can see, to declare an Integer, I use the keyword int which signals that the variable name I enter after this will be an Integer. So the below code will just declare a variable as an Integer: int height; but to give the variable “height” a value, I must assign it using an equal sign and then put a corresponding value that matches the variable type: int shoe_size = 20; So after the variable type, I can name it any name I want, but it cannot contain ANY spaces, because any space seperates different parts of the program instructions. So all of the following are valid variable names: hello_world; silly_cat_videos; broken_latptop_that_I_dontWant; camelBackNotationAlsoWorks; Woohoo_Big_summer_Blowout; Floats, are not much different: float this_is_a_float = 10.9; float pi = 3.1415; And similarly, we can declare Strings and characters: String name = &quot;Bob&quot;; char initial = 'B'; As you can see, with this tool of storing values in different types of variables, we can allow certain “programmable” ideas in our code. Arithmetic I want to quickly touch on how we can use these variables in our program. Adding Integers: int num1 = 5; int num2 = 10; int num3 = num1 + num2; Here I just declared a new Integer Variable that is set to (equal sign) the sum (by using the + sign) of num1 and num2; This is how variables are used, you can just call their value later by refrencing their variable name. Below is how we can “increment” values: num3 = num3 + num2; How this works is that we set the memory space for num3 to what num3 is now plus num2. So every time this line of code is run, num2 is added to num3. The above is equavalent to the below, just a different notation: num3 += num2; I can also subtract: num3 -= num1; multiply: num3 *= num2; or divide: num3 /= num1; Functions So let’s say you have a piece of code that you want to use in multiple places in your program. There are two options: either copy/paste that code every time, or have some variable declaration that is actually a ‘mini program’ that will run that piece of code every time you call it. In modern programming, this is called functions. In our Aruino C++ Programming language, here is how we make a function: int number = 0; void function1() { number = number + 1; } So now, every time I want to increment number, instead of writing that line of code, and just simply call the function. Let’s break the above code apart; the void key word refers to what this function will return. Every function can return a value, say I’m making a calculation, I can have a function return or output the final value of the math calculation. So when we define a function, we have to define which type of variable will it return. In this case, we made it a void (which is nothing, basically), which means this function will not return anything. But now let’s say I want to increment the number by a variable amount, how would I do that: int amount = 5; int number = 0; void function2(int addAmount) { number += addAmount; } In the parenthesis of the function, I can make a variable, in this case an Integer named addAmount, and I can refrence that in the code. Here is how I would use this function: function2(4); So here, number is incremented by 4 instead of 1 in function1. All of the code is written in between the parenthesis, that is what defines the function code, everything in between the parenthesis. Again, like all the other things, I will go in more detail once we actually start coding! Arduino Sketches, revisited So now that we know about functions, we can see that the setup() and loop() sections in the Arduino IDE, are really just functions that are already defined for us. In these functions, we will write our main code, but we can also make our own functions! In the following lessons, we will write code to accomplish tasks using these two; this lesson was just an introductary lesson for coding.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How to get started with Engineering | Hello World Example</title>
      <link href="https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-hello-world" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to get started with Engineering | Hello World Example" />
      <published>2024-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-hello-world</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-hello-world">&lt;p&gt;In this lesson, we will implement our first Arduino Project: our very own Hello World example!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Required Materials:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arduino Board (with USB cable)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Breadboard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Male-Male Jumper Wires&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arduino IDE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 LED&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 1K Ohm Resistor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how this will work, this program will print out “Hello, World” and blink an LED every 1 second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please get out your breadboard and the required components above from your &lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/How-to-start-Arduino#getting-started-with-arduino&quot;&gt;Elegoo Kit&lt;/a&gt; and wire the below diagram:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/arduinoEng/arduino_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the Arduino pin 8 connects to a resistor, which is connected to an LED. How this works is that electrons from the negative pin will flow through the resistor and LED only if the Arduino Pin 8 is open, or has a positive charge. Because if it doesn’t, then there will be no charge potential, thus the electrons won’t flow. At a microscopic level, what is going on is a transistor is opening its gate, allowing electrons to flow, thus eluminating the LED. This function is controlled by binary code, that is processed in some central processing unit in the chip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below, is the code which I will be using, please try to follow along with your own Arduino IDE. Unfortunetly, I cannot go through teaching programming in this course, but I will try to explain everything as I go along. But, I highly suggest you check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.arduino.cc/learn/programming/reference/&quot;&gt;this Arduino Refrence&lt;/a&gt; to get in depth knowledge of C++.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first started to learn the Arduino Programming language, I kept a journal of various functions or names, and every day my goal was to learn five new “names”. I tried to memorize all the symbols and what they meant, but I later figured out that it is much faster to learn programming while applying it and programming along with a tutorial, not trying to memorize every function or symbol. So if you are worried you don’t understand how C++ works, don’t worry! Just try your best to understand/follow along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// defines a comment&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledPin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// defines an integer variable names ledPin&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;outputString&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello, World&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// defines a string (a bunch of characters) variable, named output String&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delayTime&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// defines an integer (called int) variable, named delayTime&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;begin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;9600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;//Start the serial communication protocol &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pinMode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;OUTPUT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Starting program...&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;outputString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;HIGH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delayTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;outputString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delayTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I declare three variables to be used in the program:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledPin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;outputString&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello, World&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delayTime&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I initialize some “setting” in a part of the program that will only run once, the setup() function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;begin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;9600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;//Start the serial communication protocol &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pinMode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;OUTPUT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Starting program...&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This program doesn’t loop, and it runs once, at the beginning of the program. However, the main() function will loop indefinitely until the Arduino looses power:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;outputString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;HIGH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delayTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;outputString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ledPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delayTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the above code will blink the LED to infinity!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the &lt;em&gt;pinMode()&lt;/em&gt; function sets the pin we want to use and how we want to use it, either INPUT or OUTPUT. And the key function that allows us to do this blinking is &lt;em&gt;digitalWrite()&lt;/em&gt; which takes in an integer for the pin number and whether it needs to go HIGH or LOW (can also use 1 or 0). The delay happens with the &lt;em&gt;delay()&lt;/em&gt; function, which takes in milliseconds to stop execution for that period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s interesting right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare how easy this is to making an electronic circuit to &lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/Simple-Oscillator&quot;&gt;blink an LED manually&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;experimentation&quot;&gt;Experimentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to you go in and manually and adjust the time between blinks, if necessary, use the &lt;em&gt;delayMicroseconds()&lt;/em&gt; function to get smaller intervals. Once you get to a small enough number, you &lt;strong&gt;shouldn’t be able to see a blink&lt;/strong&gt;! WHY is this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pwm-pulse-width-modulation&quot;&gt;PWM (Pulse Width Modulation)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modifying the amount of time between a signal can be referred to as PWM (Pulse Width Modulation) because we are modifying (or modulating) the width (or the amount of time the pulse/signal is sent).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concept of PWM is actually how all modern computers work; they use PWM on computer screens or smartphones to adjust the brightness, and refresh the screen (and others).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what this does is two fold. First, it blinks so fast, that our eyes cannot see it blink, so it just looks constantly on. Can you see how we could use this to “adjust” the brightness of the LED by using PWM?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is simple, just adjust the ratio the LED stays on to how long it stays off when doing PWM. So in the code above, you might want to have the first delay be a little bit longer than the second one, which will make it seem brighter compared to the second one being off longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;serial-monitor&quot;&gt;Serial Monitor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next and final part of this is viewing print statements in the Arduino IDE. So, as you saw in the code, I used the built-in &lt;em&gt;Serial&lt;/em&gt; library to access the serial monitor from the Arduino. I first initialize it at a baud rate (basically how fast we communicate):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;being&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;9600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now in the loop, to print out a string, you can run the below function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;outputString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;here, we call the &lt;em&gt;println()&lt;/em&gt; function from the &lt;em&gt;Serial&lt;/em&gt; class. To prove that this works, you can open the Serial Monitor by clicking the &lt;em&gt;Serial Monitor&lt;/em&gt; button in the top right corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was quite a simple example, which is why it is often referred to as the Hello World Example. I hope this got you excited to learn more about Engineering with Arduino!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you next time!!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name></name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="arduino" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In this lesson, we will implement our first Arduino Project: our very own Hello World example!! Required Materials: Arduino Board (with USB cable) Breadboard Male-Male Jumper Wires Arduino IDE 1 LED 1 1K Ohm Resistor Here is how this will work, this program will print out “Hello, World” and blink an LED every 1 second. Please get out your breadboard and the required components above from your Elegoo Kit and wire the below diagram: As you can see, the Arduino pin 8 connects to a resistor, which is connected to an LED. How this works is that electrons from the negative pin will flow through the resistor and LED only if the Arduino Pin 8 is open, or has a positive charge. Because if it doesn’t, then there will be no charge potential, thus the electrons won’t flow. At a microscopic level, what is going on is a transistor is opening its gate, allowing electrons to flow, thus eluminating the LED. This function is controlled by binary code, that is processed in some central processing unit in the chip. Below, is the code which I will be using, please try to follow along with your own Arduino IDE. Unfortunetly, I cannot go through teaching programming in this course, but I will try to explain everything as I go along. But, I highly suggest you check out this Arduino Refrence to get in depth knowledge of C++. When I first started to learn the Arduino Programming language, I kept a journal of various functions or names, and every day my goal was to learn five new “names”. I tried to memorize all the symbols and what they meant, but I later figured out that it is much faster to learn programming while applying it and programming along with a tutorial, not trying to memorize every function or symbol. So if you are worried you don’t understand how C++ works, don’t worry! Just try your best to understand/follow along. // defines a comment int ledPin = 8; // defines an integer variable names ledPin String outputString = &quot;Hello, World&quot;; // defines a string (a bunch of characters) variable, named output String int delayTime = 1000; // defines an integer (called int) variable, named delayTime void setup() { Serial.begin(9600); //Start the serial communication protocol pinMode(ledPin, OUTPUT); digitalWrite(ledPin, LOW); Serial.println(&quot;Starting program...&quot;); } void main() { Serial.println(outputString); digitalWrite(ledPin, HIGH); delay(delayTime); Serial.println(outputString); digitalWrite(ledPin, LOW); delay(delayTime); } First, I declare three variables to be used in the program: int ledPin = 8; String outputString = &quot;Hello, World&quot;; int delayTime = 1000; Then I initialize some “setting” in a part of the program that will only run once, the setup() function: void setup() { Serial.begin(9600); //Start the serial communication protocol pinMode(ledPin, OUTPUT); digitalWrite(ledPin, LOW); Serial.println(&quot;Starting program...&quot;); } This program doesn’t loop, and it runs once, at the beginning of the program. However, the main() function will loop indefinitely until the Arduino looses power: void main() { Serial.println(outputString); digitalWrite(ledPin, HIGH); delay(delayTime); Serial.println(outputString); digitalWrite(ledPin, LOW); delay(delayTime); } the above code will blink the LED to infinity! the pinMode() function sets the pin we want to use and how we want to use it, either INPUT or OUTPUT. And the key function that allows us to do this blinking is digitalWrite() which takes in an integer for the pin number and whether it needs to go HIGH or LOW (can also use 1 or 0). The delay happens with the delay() function, which takes in milliseconds to stop execution for that period of time. So that’s interesting right? Compare how easy this is to making an electronic circuit to blink an LED manually! Experimentation I want to you go in and manually and adjust the time between blinks, if necessary, use the delayMicroseconds() function to get smaller intervals. Once you get to a small enough number, you shouldn’t be able to see a blink! WHY is this? PWM (Pulse Width Modulation) Modifying the amount of time between a signal can be referred to as PWM (Pulse Width Modulation) because we are modifying (or modulating) the width (or the amount of time the pulse/signal is sent). This concept of PWM is actually how all modern computers work; they use PWM on computer screens or smartphones to adjust the brightness, and refresh the screen (and others). So what this does is two fold. First, it blinks so fast, that our eyes cannot see it blink, so it just looks constantly on. Can you see how we could use this to “adjust” the brightness of the LED by using PWM? The answer is simple, just adjust the ratio the LED stays on to how long it stays off when doing PWM. So in the code above, you might want to have the first delay be a little bit longer than the second one, which will make it seem brighter compared to the second one being off longer. Serial Monitor The next and final part of this is viewing print statements in the Arduino IDE. So, as you saw in the code, I used the built-in Serial library to access the serial monitor from the Arduino. I first initialize it at a baud rate (basically how fast we communicate): Serial.being(9600); So now in the loop, to print out a string, you can run the below function: Serial.println(outputString); here, we call the println() function from the Serial class. To prove that this works, you can open the Serial Monitor by clicking the Serial Monitor button in the top right corner. This was quite a simple example, which is why it is often referred to as the Hello World Example. I hope this got you excited to learn more about Engineering with Arduino!! See you next time!!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How to get started with Engineering | Sensors &amp;amp; Actuators</title>
      <link href="https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-sensors" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to get started with Engineering | Sensors &amp; Actuators" />
      <published>2024-07-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-07-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-sensors</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-sensors">&lt;p&gt;One of the main applications of an Arduino board is by utilizing various sensors, actuators, and other devices&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;common-sensors&quot;&gt;Common Sensors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are simple introductions to simple/common sensors for Arduino. These usually don’t require extra software (a library) to operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;photosensors&quot;&gt;Photosensors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or sometimes called, photoresistors, these are electronic components that will change their electrical resistance based off how many photons hit its sensitive surface. I have talked about this sensor in &lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/arduino-electronics#my-technical-report-on-photoresistors&quot;&gt;my report in this previous lesson&lt;/a&gt;, and I hope you go back to that and review!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, this is a sensor that is made up of specific materials that have semi-conductive properties. At its normal state, it will have some resistance to electrical flow. However, when photons hit its sensitive service, they will make electrons change energy states, either allowing more or less resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a super short script that will show you how to use this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;begin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;9600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Let's begin!&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;loop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;analogRead&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;A2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;//read value (voltage potential) from Analog Pin 2&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;50&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To hook it up, just connect one end of the photoresistor to ground and the other end to Analog Pin 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And once you compile the script, you can experiment by putting your hand over the sensor and observing how the values change from the  Serial Monitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;touch-sensors&quot;&gt;Touch Sensors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are multiple different modules you can buy for a touch sensor, but these are a waste of money as a simple wire can be a touch sensor. I have detailed how to build a touch sensor in &lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/Touch-Delay&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; lesson. Please go back to that lesson and build that circuit at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in that post I used just electronic components. But how can we use arduino with this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, once you build that circuit on your breadboard, all we have to do to measure the output, is connect the output of the transistor to an Arduino Analog Pin. Pick any you would like, and you can run the code below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;being&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;9600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;loop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;v&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;analogRead&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;A3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;//read Analog Pin 3, or anyother pin you choose&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;v&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- ## Joystick

## Water Level Sensor --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;library---sensors&quot;&gt;Library - Sensors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are sensors that may require a library to some extra knowlegde to operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;temperature-and-humidity&quot;&gt;Temperature and Humidity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you are gardening plants in a greenhouse and you need an automated way to collect the temperature and humidity, how will you accomplish this? Well, you can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://store-usa.arduino.cc/products/grove-temperature-humidity-sensor-pro?srsltid=AfmBOoqYoffAkhPifA9yp4xX23G8pze6Jj0sfVQu1lXpHfzy7GpCsR8A&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; module. There should be a temperature sensor in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://burakayy.com/blog/How-to-start-Arduino#getting-started-with-arduino&quot;&gt;Elegoo Kit&lt;/a&gt;, which you can follow along with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this sensor, there are three main pins: ground, power, and an output pin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connect the power pin and ground to 5v and ground on your arduino, respectively. Then, connect the output pin to a digital pin on the Arduino:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/arduinoEng/temp1.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, to use this we will use a library provided by the producers to help us out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#include &amp;lt;dht.h&amp;gt; //this is how you include a library in Arduino
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dht&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DHT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#define DHT11_PIN 2
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(){&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;being&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;9600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;loop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DHT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;read11&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DHT11_PIN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Temperature: &quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DHT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;temperature&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;223&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Humidity: &quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DHT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;humidity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;%&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;500&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s walk through how this code works. First, we include the dht library in the first line. Then we create a dht object, named &lt;em&gt;DHT&lt;/em&gt;, and define the pin which it’s connected to Digital Pin 2. Once we initialize the Serial connection in setup, we read the value from our defined pin variable and put that value into an integer. But to get our actual temperature and humidity values, we need to reference them from the built in dht class; they are set in the &lt;em&gt;temperature&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;humidity&lt;/em&gt; values. Finally, we print them out twice every second (or once every .5 seconds).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the range/accuracy for the DHT sensor:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humidity Range: 20-90% RH&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humidity Accuracy: ±5% RH&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Temperature Range: 0-50 °C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Temperature Accuracy: ±2% °C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Operating Voltage: 3V to 5.5V&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dht sensor measures relative humidity, which is basically the amount of water vapor in the air vs. the saturation point of water vapor in the air. This saturation point is when water vapor starts to condense and leave behind due on surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The saturation point changes with air temperature. Cold air can hold less water vapor before it becomes saturated, and hot air can hold more water vapor before it becomes saturated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formula to calculate relative humidity is:&lt;/p&gt;

\[RH = (\frac{P_w}{P_s}) X \cdot 100%\]

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RH = relative humidity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;density of water vapor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;density of water vapor at saturation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how can we use this to measure temperature and humidity. Well, this sensor is made up of two electrodes and a substrate. When water vapor accumulates on this surfaces, it will release ions, changing the conductivity between the electrodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the temperature part, it will basically measure the resistance a certain material makes, which depends on the temperature. However, since the Arduino can’t directly measure resistance, it will measure voltage from a voltage divider, which is defined by this equation:&lt;/p&gt;

\[V_{out} = V_{in} \cdot (\frac{R2}{R1 + R2})\]

&lt;p&gt;Where R1 and R2 are resistors in series. If one of these is a constant resistor, and the other is the thermistor, then we can rearange and calculate for the resistance, which we can convert to temperature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;pir-motion-sensors&quot;&gt;PIR Motion Sensors&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a motion sensor that utilizes changes in IR (Infared Red) Light. It basically has hemispheres with sensors in it, and when there is a gradient from one to another, it will send a pin high (from a 0 to a 1). We will need to read this using Arduino Analog Pins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To connect this, the pinout is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GND – connect to ground&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OUT – connect to an Arduino digital pin&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5V – connect to 5V&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sensorPin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;val&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;being&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;9600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pinMode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sensorPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;INPUT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;loop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalRead&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sensorPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;HIGH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Motion detected&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;No Motion&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;200&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This code is pretty simple, as all we do is do a digital read on the sensor output pin, and if it is high, then we say there was motion on the serial monitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ultrasound-sensors&quot;&gt;Ultrasound Sensors&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, this sensor is actually quite interesting. To introduce it, this sensor is basically a proximity sensor that uses sound waves. You can think of it like a radar, it sends out a sound wave, and listens for the time between when it will return, and since we know the speed of sound we can use math to calculate the distance an object is from us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the first thing we have to do is to hook this up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GND - to Arduino ground&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VCC - to Arduino 5v&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trig - to Arduino digital pin 9&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Echo - to Arduino digital pin 10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, now time for the fun part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s first understand how this sensor works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this sensor, there are two main ‘tubes’, one of them is kind of like a speaker for ultrasonic sound, and the other one is a receiver for this sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/arduinoEng/ultra1.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transmitter emits a “ping” (sound for a short period of time) and that sound bounces off an object, returning to the sound sensor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how can we calculate the distance an object is away, given this information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, consider this equation:&lt;/p&gt;

\[distance = speed \cdot time\]

&lt;p&gt;And we know the speed of sound to be 343 meters/second. But since the distance the sound travels after first released from speaker is twice the distance from the object (back and forth, round trip), our equation will be:&lt;/p&gt;

\[distance = \frac{(343 \cdot time)}{2}\]

&lt;p&gt;Now, all we have to do is count the time between the first ping and the returning signal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how do we send a ping in the first place? Well, for this specific module, all we have to do is send a “trigger” signal, that goes HIGH for 10 milliseconds. This will cause the module (which has on board electronics to control this) to send out an 8 cycle ping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so using this knowlegde, we can use this sensor to calculate the distance an object is away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to get us started, below is the code I will be using:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;trigPin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;echoPin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// define some variables&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;long&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pinMode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;trigPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;OUTPUT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Sets the trigPin as an Output&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pinMode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;echoPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;INPUT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Sets the echoPin as an Input&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;begin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;9600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Starts the serial communication (check serial monitor)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;loop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Clears the trigPin&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;trigPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delayMicroseconds&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Sets the trigPin on HIGH state for 10 micro seconds&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;trigPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;HIGH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delayMicroseconds&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;trigPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Reads the echoPin, returns the sound wave travel time in microseconds&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;duration&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pulseIn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;echoPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;HIGH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Calculating the distance&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;duration&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.034&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Prints the distance on the Serial Monitor&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Distance: &quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Serial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I somewhat cheated as I am using a built-in function to measure the time taken, using the &lt;em&gt;pulseIn()&lt;/em&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ---
explain with better, paul's code
--- --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But anyways, as you can see, with this code I send out a ping:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;trigPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;HIGH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;delayMicroseconds&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digitalWrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;trigPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;LOW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and then, with the below function, I measure how long it would take for the echoPin to go HIGH:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;duration&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pulseIn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;echoPin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;HIGH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, since we know the speed of sound, and the time the sound wave took (round-trip), we can calculate the distance to the object:&lt;/p&gt;

\[distance = velocity \cdot time
\\\\
distance = 0.034 \cdot duration\]

&lt;p&gt;Which would give us the distance of the object twice, because the wave travels to and back to the object, so we have to divide by 2:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-cpp highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;duration&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.034&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you view the Serial Monitor, you will see print outs of the ditance measurement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very useful sensor, I have used this for making a sonar, which I suggect you try yourself!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- # IR Reciever

While this can also be used for a proximity sensor, in this case, we won't be doing that. The IR sensor simply receives IR (Infared Red) light. 

# Inertial Measurement Units (IMU)

In my opinion, one of the most important sensors for your robotics projects, the IMU is basically an orientation sensor. It will measure your acceleration and gyroscopic rotation. How it works is really fancy, so I will try to simplify it. 



To use it with your Arduino, you can check out [this past blog post](https://burakayy.com/blog/IMU-Measurments) for more information.

Ok, since I linked a previous lesson on how to use IMUs, I will keep this section pretty short. 


# Actuators | Motors

Now, we move into actuators. The first thing I want to talk about are motors. 

## DC Motors

### Using Low Voltage Motors with Arduino

### Using High Voltage Motors with Arduino | Motor Drivers

## Stepper Motors

## Servo Motors

Lastly, maybe on of the most useful types of motors for your Engineering Projects, 
 --&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name></name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="arduino" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the main applications of an Arduino board is by utilizing various sensors, actuators, and other devices Common Sensors Below are simple introductions to simple/common sensors for Arduino. These usually don’t require extra software (a library) to operate. Photosensors Or sometimes called, photoresistors, these are electronic components that will change their electrical resistance based off how many photons hit its sensitive surface. I have talked about this sensor in my report in this previous lesson, and I hope you go back to that and review! Basically, this is a sensor that is made up of specific materials that have semi-conductive properties. At its normal state, it will have some resistance to electrical flow. However, when photons hit its sensitive service, they will make electrons change energy states, either allowing more or less resistance. Below is a super short script that will show you how to use this: void setup() { Serial.begin(9600); Serial.println(&quot;Let's begin!&quot;); } void loop() { int value = analogRead(A2); //read value (voltage potential) from Analog Pin 2 Serial.println(value); delay(50); } To hook it up, just connect one end of the photoresistor to ground and the other end to Analog Pin 2. And once you compile the script, you can experiment by putting your hand over the sensor and observing how the values change from the Serial Monitor. Touch Sensors There are multiple different modules you can buy for a touch sensor, but these are a waste of money as a simple wire can be a touch sensor. I have detailed how to build a touch sensor in this lesson. Please go back to that lesson and build that circuit at the end. However, in that post I used just electronic components. But how can we use arduino with this? Well, once you build that circuit on your breadboard, all we have to do to measure the output, is connect the output of the transistor to an Arduino Analog Pin. Pick any you would like, and you can run the code below: void setup() { Serial.being(9600); } void loop() { int v = analogRead(A3); //read Analog Pin 3, or anyother pin you choose Serial.println(v); delay(10); } Library - Sensors These are sensors that may require a library to some extra knowlegde to operate. Temperature and Humidity Let’s say you are gardening plants in a greenhouse and you need an automated way to collect the temperature and humidity, how will you accomplish this? Well, you can use this module. There should be a temperature sensor in the Elegoo Kit, which you can follow along with. In this sensor, there are three main pins: ground, power, and an output pin. Connect the power pin and ground to 5v and ground on your arduino, respectively. Then, connect the output pin to a digital pin on the Arduino: Then, to use this we will use a library provided by the producers to help us out: #include &amp;lt;dht.h&amp;gt; //this is how you include a library in Arduino dht DHT; #define DHT11_PIN 2 void setup(){ Serial.being(9600); } void loop() { int value = DHT.read11(DHT11_PIN); Serial.print(&quot;Temperature: &quot;); Serial.print(DHT.temperature); Serial.println((char)223); Serial.print(&quot;Humidity: &quot;); Serial.print(DHT.humidity); Serial.println(&quot;%&quot;); delay(500); } Let’s walk through how this code works. First, we include the dht library in the first line. Then we create a dht object, named DHT, and define the pin which it’s connected to Digital Pin 2. Once we initialize the Serial connection in setup, we read the value from our defined pin variable and put that value into an integer. But to get our actual temperature and humidity values, we need to reference them from the built in dht class; they are set in the temperature and humidity values. Finally, we print them out twice every second (or once every .5 seconds). Below is the range/accuracy for the DHT sensor: Humidity Range: 20-90% RH Humidity Accuracy: ±5% RH Temperature Range: 0-50 °C Temperature Accuracy: ±2% °C Operating Voltage: 3V to 5.5V This dht sensor measures relative humidity, which is basically the amount of water vapor in the air vs. the saturation point of water vapor in the air. This saturation point is when water vapor starts to condense and leave behind due on surfaces. The saturation point changes with air temperature. Cold air can hold less water vapor before it becomes saturated, and hot air can hold more water vapor before it becomes saturated. The formula to calculate relative humidity is: \[RH = (\frac{P_w}{P_s}) X \cdot 100%\] RH = relative humidity density of water vapor density of water vapor at saturation So how can we use this to measure temperature and humidity. Well, this sensor is made up of two electrodes and a substrate. When water vapor accumulates on this surfaces, it will release ions, changing the conductivity between the electrodes. For the temperature part, it will basically measure the resistance a certain material makes, which depends on the temperature. However, since the Arduino can’t directly measure resistance, it will measure voltage from a voltage divider, which is defined by this equation: \[V_{out} = V_{in} \cdot (\frac{R2}{R1 + R2})\] Where R1 and R2 are resistors in series. If one of these is a constant resistor, and the other is the thermistor, then we can rearange and calculate for the resistance, which we can convert to temperature. PIR Motion Sensors This is a motion sensor that utilizes changes in IR (Infared Red) Light. It basically has hemispheres with sensors in it, and when there is a gradient from one to another, it will send a pin high (from a 0 to a 1). We will need to read this using Arduino Analog Pins. To connect this, the pinout is as follows: GND – connect to ground OUT – connect to an Arduino digital pin 5V – connect to 5V int sensorPin = 2; int val; void setup() { Serial.being(9600); pinMode(sensorPin, INPUT); } void loop() { val = digitalRead(sensorPin); if (val == HIGH) { Serial.println(&quot;Motion detected&quot;); }else { Serial.println(&quot;No Motion&quot;); } delay(200); } This code is pretty simple, as all we do is do a digital read on the sensor output pin, and if it is high, then we say there was motion on the serial monitor. Ultrasound Sensors Ok, this sensor is actually quite interesting. To introduce it, this sensor is basically a proximity sensor that uses sound waves. You can think of it like a radar, it sends out a sound wave, and listens for the time between when it will return, and since we know the speed of sound we can use math to calculate the distance an object is from us. So, the first thing we have to do is to hook this up: GND - to Arduino ground VCC - to Arduino 5v Trig - to Arduino digital pin 9 Echo - to Arduino digital pin 10 Okay, now time for the fun part. Let’s first understand how this sensor works: On this sensor, there are two main ‘tubes’, one of them is kind of like a speaker for ultrasonic sound, and the other one is a receiver for this sound. The transmitter emits a “ping” (sound for a short period of time) and that sound bounces off an object, returning to the sound sensor. So, how can we calculate the distance an object is away, given this information. Well, consider this equation: \[distance = speed \cdot time\] And we know the speed of sound to be 343 meters/second. But since the distance the sound travels after first released from speaker is twice the distance from the object (back and forth, round trip), our equation will be: \[distance = \frac{(343 \cdot time)}{2}\] Now, all we have to do is count the time between the first ping and the returning signal. But how do we send a ping in the first place? Well, for this specific module, all we have to do is send a “trigger” signal, that goes HIGH for 10 milliseconds. This will cause the module (which has on board electronics to control this) to send out an 8 cycle ping. Ok, so using this knowlegde, we can use this sensor to calculate the distance an object is away. So, to get us started, below is the code I will be using: int trigPin = 9; int echoPin = 10; // define some variables long duration; int distance; void setup() { pinMode(trigPin, OUTPUT); // Sets the trigPin as an Output pinMode(echoPin, INPUT); // Sets the echoPin as an Input Serial.begin(9600); // Starts the serial communication (check serial monitor) } void loop() { // Clears the trigPin digitalWrite(trigPin, LOW); delayMicroseconds(2); // Sets the trigPin on HIGH state for 10 micro seconds digitalWrite(trigPin, HIGH); delayMicroseconds(10); digitalWrite(trigPin, LOW); // Reads the echoPin, returns the sound wave travel time in microseconds duration = pulseIn(echoPin, HIGH); // Calculating the distance distance = duration * 0.034 / 2; // Prints the distance on the Serial Monitor Serial.print(&quot;Distance: &quot;); Serial.println(distance); } Here, I somewhat cheated as I am using a built-in function to measure the time taken, using the pulseIn() function. But anyways, as you can see, with this code I send out a ping: digitalWrite(trigPin, HIGH); delayMicroseconds(10); digitalWrite(trigPin, LOW); and then, with the below function, I measure how long it would take for the echoPin to go HIGH: duration = pulseIn(echoPin, HIGH); Now, since we know the speed of sound, and the time the sound wave took (round-trip), we can calculate the distance to the object: \[distance = velocity \cdot time \\\\ distance = 0.034 \cdot duration\] Which would give us the distance of the object twice, because the wave travels to and back to the object, so we have to divide by 2: distance = duration * 0.034 / 2; Now, if you view the Serial Monitor, you will see print outs of the ditance measurement. This is a very useful sensor, I have used this for making a sonar, which I suggect you try yourself!!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
